Kirk Munroe Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Kirk Munroe Papers 1850-1940 1867-1932
MSS33894
Munroe, Kirk, 1850-1930
2,500 items
24 containers plus 2 oversize
10 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Author and adventurer. Correspondence, diaries, handwritten drafts and printed copies of writings, biographical material, scrapbooks, subject files, newspaper clippings, printed matter, photographs, drawings, and other papers relating primarily to Munroe's literary career and travels, including on a survey teams for the Union Pacific Railroad Company and the Atchison, Topeka, and Santa Fe Railway Company.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Munroe, Kirk, 1850-1930.; Munroe, Mabel Stearns. Mabel Stearns Munroe papers.; Munroe, Mary Barr. Mary Barr Munroe papers.
Organizations
Atchison, Topeka, and Santa Fe Railway Company.; Union Pacific Railroad Company.
Subjects
Canoes and canoeing.; Cycling.; Indians of North America--Florida.; Literature.; Railroads--Surveying.; Seminole Indians.
Places
East Asia--Description and travel.; Everglades (Fla.)--Description and travel.; Florida--Description and travel.; Hudson Bay--Description and travel.
Occupations
Adventurers.; Authors.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Kirk Munroe, author and adventurer, were given to the Library of Congress by Eliot O’Hara in 1964.
Transfers
A daguerreotype and two tintypes have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Kirk Munroe are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of the 1915 Mary Barr Munroe diary in the Munroe Papers is available on one reel. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available
Biographical Note
Date Event
1850, Sept. 15 Born Charles Kirk Munroe, Prairie du Chien, Wis
1867 1868 Explored and surveyed routes for the Union Pacific Railroad Co. and Atchison, Topeka, and Santa Fe Railway Co.
1868 1869 Attended Lawrence Scientific School of Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1876 1879 Reporter, New York Sun and New York Times
1879 1882 Editor, Harper’s Round Table
1880 Founded League of American Wheelmen
1883 Married Mary Barr (died 1922)
1886 Settled in Coconut Grove, Miami, Fla. Published Wakulla; A Story of Adventure in Florida. New York and London: Harper & Brothers
1887 Published The Flamingo Feather. New York: Harper & Brothers, Franklin Square
1888 Published Derrick Sterling; A Story of Mines. New York: Harper & Brothers
1890 1891 Traveled from Coconut Grove, Fla., to the Ten Thousand Islands in sailboat Allapata
1900 Published Under the Great Bear. New York: Doubleday, Page & Co.
1905 Became a real estate developer, Miami-Dade County, Fla. Published For the Mikado. New York and London: Harper & Brothers
1924 Married Mabel Stearns
1930, June 16 Died, Miami, Fla.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Kirk Munroe (1850-1930) consist of diaries, correspondence, writings biographical material, photographs, subject files, printed matter, newspaper clippings, memorabilia, scrapbooks, drawings and watercolors, and an autographed guest book from “The Scrubub,” the Munroe home in Florida. The material extends from 1850 to 1940, with the bulk of the papers concentrated in the period 1867-1932. The collection is organized into four series: Diaries; General Correspondence; Article, Short Story and Book File; and Miscellany.
The papers relate primarily to Kirk Munroe’s literary career as an author of boy’s books; his adventures on a survey team for the Union Pacific and Atchison, Topeka, and Santa Fe railroads; trips into the Everglades, into the Hudson Bay region, and to the Far East on a world tour; his work in behalf of the Seminole people of Florida; and his canoeing and bicycling interests. These activities are documented principally by his writings, by the correspondence kept by himself and his two wives, by the diaries kept by himself, and by his first scrapbooks. The writings include handwritten drafts and printed copies of articles, short stories, essays, books, and poetry. The period of his life from 1870 to 1880 is poorly documented.
A diary dated 1853 was kept by Charles W. Munroe, Kirk Munroe’s father. Diaries dated 1867-1869, 1881, and 1923 were kept by Kirk Munroe. Diaries dated 1884-1922 were kept by Mary Barr Munroe, first wife of Kirk Munroe. There are no diaries for the years 1870-1880.
Correspondence to and from Kirk Munroe is meager and focused exclusively on his family for the years 1867-1869. There is considerable correspondence to and from his second wife, Mabel Stearns Munroe, with reference to a proposed biography of Kirk. Her correspondents include Poultney Bigelow, Frank W. Buxton, Randolph Edgar, Duncan U. Fletcher, Ward Greene, Hermann Hagedorn, James K. Hand, Arthur Milton Pope, Herbert Putnam, William F. Raney, Clement Francis Robinson, William A. Rodgers, Charles Scribner (1854-1930) W. P. Stephens, Lyman Beecher Stowe, and Ray L. Wilbur.
The Miscellany series contains family and biographical material, photographs, printed matter, various topical files, and scrapbooks of miscellaneous writings, diary excerpts, correspondence. photographs, and clippings. Depicted in the photographs in addition to the Munroe family are canoeing and bicycling scenes, views from a trip to Hudson Bay in 1909, Indians, and the Monroe home in Florida. Some of these same topics are documented in a subject file within the series, which also contains oversize drawings, sketches, and watercolors.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
Diaries, 1853-1924
General Correspondence, 1850-1940
Article, Short Story, and Book File, 1869-1920
Miscellany, 1867-1940
Container List
- Diaries, 1853-1924 (Box 1-8)
  Bound diaries and folders of typed excerpts.
  Arranged chronologically.
  The diary for 1915 in Container 7 is available on microfilm, shelf no. 21,375.
  - 1853-1885 (Box 1)
  - 1886-1891 (Box 2)
  - 1892-1896 (Box 3)
  - 1897-1902 (Box 4)
  - 1903-1908 (Box 5)
  - 1909-1913 (Box 6)
  - 1914-1918 Diary for 1915 available on microfilm shelf no. 21,375 (Box 7)
  - 1919-1923 (Box 8)
- General Correspondence, 1850-1940 (Box 9-11)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged by name of person and therein chronologically.
  - Munroe family and Kirk Munroe, 1850-1930 (Box 9)
  - Munroe, Mary Barr, 1907-1921 (first wife) (Box 10)
  - Munroe, Mabel Stearns (second wife) (Box 10)
    - 1927-1931, Oct. (Box 10)
    - 1931, Nov.-1940 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
- Article, Short Story, and Book File, 1869-1920 (Box 12-18)
  Handwritten drafts and printed copies of articles, short stories, essays, books, and poetry by Munroe. Includes newspaper clippings and early newspaper articles possibly written by Munroe as a reporter; a scrapbook containing Munroe’s poetry; and bibliographies, notes, and related material..
  Arranged by type of writing or material
  - Articles and short stories, 1883-1920 (Box 12)
  - Book file (Box 12)
    - Summer in the Catskill Mountains, 1883 (Box 12)
    - Florida Annual (Box 12)
      - 1885 (Box 12)
      - 1886 (Box 12)
    - The Flamingo Feather, 1886 (Box 13)
    - Dorymatas, 1890 (Box 13)
    - Canoemates, 1893 (Box 13)
    - The White Conquerors, 1893 (Box 13)
    - The Fur Seal’s Tooth, 1894 (Box 13)
    - The Totem of the Bear, 1894 (Box 13)
    - Snow Shoes and Sledges, 1895 (Box 14)
    - Rick Dale, 1896 (Box 14)
    - Through Swamp and Glade, 1896 (Box 14)
    - The Painted Desert, 1897 (Box 14)
    - With Crockett and Bowie, 1897 (Box 14)
    - In Pirate Waters, 1898 (Box 14)
    - Forward March, 1899 (Box 15)
    - Shine Terrill, 1899 (Box 15)
    - Under the Great Bear, 1900 (Box 15)
    - Brethren of the Coast, 1900 (Box 15)
    - The Son of Satsuma, 1901 (Box 15)
    - The Belt of Seven Totems, 1902 (Box 15)
    - The Blue Dragon, 1904 (Box 16)
    - The Outcast Warrior, 1905 (Box 16)
    - For the Mikado, 1905. (Box 16)
    - “With Transit and Level”, undated (Box 16)
    - “A South Sea Rover”, undated (Box 16)
    - Golden Days of Forty-Nine, undated (Box 16)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
    - Newspaper file, 1869-1876 (Box 17)
    - Bibliography of writings, 1879-1920 (Box 17)
    - Poetry file, 1882-1885, n.d. (Box 17)
    - Notes for “A New Wilderness” and “Pioneer Women of the Northwest,” 1909 (Box 17)
    - General, 1884-1906 (Box 17)
    - Scrapbook, 1874-1909 (Oversize) (Box OV 18)
- Miscellany, 1867-1940 (Box 19-26)
  Family and biographical material, photographs, printed matter, various topical files, scrapbooks of miscellaneous writings, diary excerpts, correspondence. photographs, and clippings, and oversize drawings, sketches, and watercolors.
  Organized by type of file or material.
  - Biographical file (Box 19)
    - Obituaries, 1930 (Box 19)
    - Articles about Kirk Munroe, 1891-1937 (Box 19)
    - Notes and clippings (Box 19)
    - Family records (Box 19)
    - Material for proposed biography, 1930-1940 (Box 19)
  - Photographs (Box 20)
    - Family, 1868-1923, (3 folders) (Box 20)
    - Early days, 1886-1916 (Box 20)
    - Indians, 1886-1938, (3 folders) (Box 20)
    - Hudson Bay trip, 1909 (Box 20)
    - “The Scrububs,” Florida home, 1885-1920, (2 folders) (Box 21)
    - Bicycling, 1880, 1894 (Box 21)
    - Canoeing, 1882-1884 (Box 21)
    - Miscellany, 1872-1903 (Box 21)
  - Subject file (Box 21)
    - Canoeing, 1882-1913 (Box 21)
    - Bicycling, 1880-1938 (Box 21)
    - Indians, 1898-1922 (Box 22)
    - World tour, 1903 (Box 22)
    - New York Sun and Times, 1877-1910 (Box 22)
    - Union Pacific and Santa Fe Railroad surveying trip, 1867-1868 (Box 22)
  - Autographed guest book for “The Scrububs,” 1886-1931 (Box 23)
  - Printed matter, 1868-1932 (Box 23)
  - Short stories (Mabel S. Munroe), undated (Box 24)
  - Memorabilia, undated (Box 24)
  - General miscellany, 1869-1940 (Box 24)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 24)
    - 1886-1897 (Box 24)
    - 1877-1924 (Box 25)
  - Drawings, photostats, sketches, and watercolors, 1869-1888, undated (Oversize) (Box OV 26)